Guide to the William Harrison Hamman Papers, 1828-1966 MS 006
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
- Series III: W. H. Hamman - Business and Legal papers (Boxes 3-10), 249927
  - Address to jury representing unknown female plaintiff in land case, 249940 (Box 10)
  - Legal notes concerning deeds from John Peterson; and Susan Peterson vs. H.H. Boggs, 249939 (Box 10)
  - Field notes on John Dycke lands in Wycke County, 249938 (Box 10)
  - Transcribed letters re. Oldham vs Evans, n.d.; 249937 (Box 10)
  - Notes re. surveys in Jefferson County, n.d.; 249936 (Box 10)
  - Maps and plats of land (some showing owners), 249935 (Box 10)
  - Photograph of ore beds (New Birmingham), n.d.; 249934 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous notes re. minerals, etc. (New Birmingham), n.d.; 249933 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous notes, n.d.; 249932 (Box 10)
  - Prospectus of town of Cumberland Gap, 249931 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous printed advertisements, prospecta, n.d.; 249930 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous figures, n.d.; 249929 (Box 10)
  - Fragments, n.d.; 249928 (Box 10)
- Series IV: John Hamman - Personal and Business papers, 249897
  - Collected materials re. W. H. Hamman's legal affairs, oil interests, etc., 1866 - 1905; 249926 (Box 11)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. John Brown estate, 1905; 249925 (Box 11)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Zeller vs. Hamman, 1905 - 1906; 249924 (Box 11)
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. Joel Burt estate, 1905 - 1906; 249923 (Box 11)
  - Letters to J. Hamman re. timber, 1905 - 1906; 249922 (Box 11)
  - Inventory of books in law library, Apr. 5, 1907; 249921 (Box 11)
  - Letter from W.S. Farish re. oil land in Oklahoma, July 18, 1907; 249920 (Box 11)
  - Legal papers and correspondence - Fielder vs. Kirby, ca. 1907; 249919 (Box 11)
  - Letter to Mrs John Hamman, 1907; 249918 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence re. F.A. Sherman (with records, 1844-1872), 1907; 249917 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence from Ella Hamman, 1911 - 1925; 249916 (Box 11)
  - "Facts concerning the early romance of Houston" by Mrs. Lenoir Hunt, 1921; 249915 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence, 1924, 1966; 249914 (Box 11)
  - Moore et al v. unknown heirs of Gilchrist et al., 1925; 249913 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence re. Mrs. Ella Hamman, 1926; 249912 (Box 11)
  - Letter re. costs for resurfacing floors at 601 lovett Blvd., Dec. 7, 1927; 249911 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence from Franklin Williams (with "An Idyl of Early Texas" by Nellie Houston Bringhurst), 1937 - 1943; 249910 (Box 11)
  - Catalogues of Texas books, 1941; 249909 (Box 11)
  - Houston Post article on the Hammans ( "Texas Heartbeat" by Ed Kilman), Jan. 10, 1943; 249908 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence from John Hamman, Jr. re. oil, 1945; 249907 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence with Grover C. Ramsey re. ghost towns, 1965; 249906 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous newsclippings, n.d.; 249905 (Box 11)
  - Printed legal briefs, petitions, etc., n.d.; 249904 (Box 11)
  - Autobiographical notes, n.d.; 249903 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, notes, etc. re. Texas History (particularly Robertson County), 249902 (Box 11)
  - History of the Haman(n) - Hamman(n) surname, n.d.; 249901 (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous items re. slaves, n.d.; 249900 (Box 11)
  - Notes on Sam Houston (including signature), n.d.; 249899 (Box 11)
  - Cooper K. Ragan's address to Sons of Confederate Veterans, 1965; 249898 (Box 11)
- Series V: Hamman Family - Personal, business and other papers, 249879
  - Legal papers and correspondence re. property owned by Ella Hamman and/or the Lawdermilk family, 1822 - 1901; 249896 (Box 12)
  - Personal correspondence of Ella V. Hamman, 1866 - 1925; 249895 (Box 12)
  - Scrapbook kept by Ella V. Hamman, 1873 -?; 249894 (Box 12)
  - Business correspondence of Ella V. Hamman, 1889 - 1898; 249893 (Box 12)
  - Commerce and Industry by Ella Hamman (for the Axson Club), ca. 1917; 249892 (Box 12)
  - Will of Mrs. Ella V. Hamman, Sept. 2, 1925; 249891 (Box 12)
  - Obituary notices for Ella Hamman, June 25, 1926; 249890 (Box 12)
  - Genealogical information re. Ella Hamman's ancestors, n.d.; 249889 (Box 12)
  - A Symposium on the life of Gen. Wm. H. Hamman, by Ella Hamman, n.d.; 249888 (Box 12)
  - Alexander Hamilton, by Emma Hamman, 249887 (Box 12)
  - Speech made by Ella Hamman to the United Daughters of the Confederacy, n.d.; 249886 (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous material re. Ella Hamman, n.d.; 249885 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence - papers of John Hamman, Jr., ? - 1931; 249884 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence to Mrs Frances Transom Hamman re. her brother Frederick Transom (includes clippings re. Mrs. Frances Hamman), 1914 - 1935; 249883 (Box 12)
  - Newsclippings re. John Hamman, Jr. and George F. Hamman (sons of John Hamman), ? - 1941; 249882 (Box 12)
  - Printed invitation from Mr. and Mrs. John Hamman, 249881 (Box 12)
  - Unidentified photograph of a home, n.d.; 249880 (Box 12)
- Series VI: Oversize Materials, 249847
  - Land grant (Robertson County) to Edward McMillan, July 30, 1841; 249878 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Comal County) to Asa. W. Chambers, Feb. 25, 1845; 249877 (Drawer 33)
  - Land Grant (Robertson County) to Benjamin R. Tyers, May 7, 1856; 249876 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Haskell County) to Joshua G. Smith, May 19, 1860; 249875 (Drawer 33)
  - Broadside: Letter from Gen. Houston. His views respecting our political affairs. With handwritten note signed by Houston on reverse (encapsulated), Nov. 14, 1860; 249874 (Drawer 33)
  - Broadside: Report on resolutions made in Austin re. a call session of the legislature, or a convention of the people (encapsulated), Nov. 17, 1860; 249873 (Drawer 33)
  - Robertson County resolutions, Dec. 15, 1860; 249872; (2 copies, 1 photocopy) (Drawer 33)
  - Broadside calling for an election of delegates on January 8, 1861 (encapsulated), ca. 1861; 249871 (Drawer 33)
  - Broadside recruiting volunteers for the 15th Texas cavalry, Jan. 23, 1864; 249870 (Drawer 33)
  - W. H. Hamman's commission to Asst. Adjt. General of the 5th Brigade Dist. TST, with rank of Captain, Aug. 4, 1864; 249869 (Drawer 33)
  - W. H. Hamman's commission to Brigadier General of 5th Brigade Dist. TST, Dec. 28, 1864; 249868 (Drawer 33)
  - Drawing "Death of General Robert E. Lee", Oct. 12, 1870; 249867 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Eastland County) to William Grayham, July 19, 1872; 249866 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Robertson County) to A. Groesbeck, Oct. 8, 1874; 249865 (Drawer 33)
  - Proclamation by the presiding justice of Robertson County (encapsulated), Jan. 7, 1876; 249864 (Drawer 33)
  - Address of Col. W.H.H. Lawrence delivered before Greenback Club, no. 280 (encapsulated), May 4, 1878; 249863 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Refugio County) to James T. McGrew, June 4, 1878; 249862 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Hamilton County) to Wm. A. McGrew, June 21, 1882; 249861 (Drawer 33)
  - Map of Texas. Compliments of Sanborn and Warner, ca. 1885; 249860 (Drawer 33)
  - "A Texas Iron Industry... New Birmingham", July 7, 1888; 249859; (2 copies) (Drawer 33)
  - Revised list of lots for sale... Cherokee Land and Iron Co., Feb. 1889; 249858 (Drawer 33)
  - Revised list of lots for sale... Cherokee Land and Iron Co., March 1889; 249857; (2 copies) (Drawer 33)
  - Revised list of lots for sale by the New Birmingham Iron and Land Co., Apr. 12, 1889; 249856; (3 copies) (Drawer 33)
  - Business and Residence lots for sale by the New Birmingham Iron and Land Co., May 27, 1889; 249855; (3 copies) (Drawer 33)
  - Revised price list of property belonging to the New Birmingham Iron and Land Co., Oct. 1, 1889; 249854 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant (Hardin County) to Texas and New Orleans R.R. Co., Dec. 4, 1890; 249853 (Drawer 33)
  - Land grant of 640 acres to Martha A. Preston by J.S. Hogg, Nov. 8, 1897; 249852 (Drawer 33)
  - Advertisement "The Texas Iron Center" New Birmingham, n.d.; 249851 (Drawer 33)
  - Picture: The Presidents of the United States, n.d.; 249850 (Drawer 33)
  - Advertisement: Dr. Wilford Hall's Health Pamphlet, n.d.; 249849 (Drawer 33)
  - An address to the people of Texas by James H. Bell (in fragments), n.d.; 249848 (Drawer 33)
- Series VII: Newspapers, 249802
  - Chicago, Illinois The Sentinel 2:13:, February 26, 1880.; 249846; 8pp. (Drawer 37, Folder 1)
  - The Sentinel 12:43:, September 11, 1890.; 249845; 8pp. (Drawer 37, Folder 1)
  - Austin: The Daily State Gazette: 6:170: 4pp., July 21, 1873.; 249844 (Drawer 37, Folder 1)
  - Franklin: The Central Texan: 7:32: 4pp. (2 copies)., July 17, 1890.; 249843 (Drawer 37, Folder 1)
  - Calvert: The Calvert Tribune: 1:37: 4pp., January 6, 1871.; 249842 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Calvert Tribune: 48:11: 8pp. (14 copies+ additional pgs), June 25, 1926.; 249841 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Calvert Tribune: 2pp.,"Extra"; Election returns., November 12, 1872.; 249840 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Central Texan: 3:19: 4pp. (3 copies), October 25, 1872.; 249839 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Central Texan: 3:20: 2pp., November 1, 1872.; 249838 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Central Texan: extra: broadside., November 12, 1872.; 249837 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Central Texan:, October 9, 1873.; 249836 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - The Vox Populi: 11:46: 2pp., August 5, 1887.; 249835 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - Texas White Ribbon: 1:12: 8pp., September 1890.; 249834 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - Dallas Morning News: 2pp.(fragment), November 6, 1887.; 249833 (Drawer 37, Folder 2)
  - Washington, D.C.: The Sunday Star: 2pp., magazine section, November 7, 1920.; 249832 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - New York: Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper: 8pp., "Indiana Supplement", January 19, 1889.; 249831 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Nashville: The Nashville American: 22:7898: 2pp., July 25, 1898.; 249830 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Galveston: The Galveston Daily: 34:310: 4pp., January 7, 1876.; 249829 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Galveston Daily News: 47:181: 8pp., October 25, 1888.; 249828 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Galveston Tri-Weekly News: 23:157: 4pp., July 28, 1865.; 249827 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Galveston Weekly News: 22:20: 4pp., August 16, 1865.; 249826 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Groesbeck, TX: Rising Sun: extra: broadside., September 12, 1878.; 249825 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Harriman, TX: Harriman Daily Advance: 1:1: 4pp., April 8, 1890.; 249824 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Hearne, TX: The Hearne Enterprise: 2:16: 4pp., January 20, 1876.; 249823 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Hearne Enterprise: 2:17: 4pp., January 27, 1876.; 249822 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Texas Free Press: extra: broadside., October 9, 1872.; 249821 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Texas Free Press: 1:11: 4pp., October 30, 1872.; 249820 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Texas Free Press: 1:12: 4pp., November 6, 1872.; 249819 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Daily Post: 8:269: 2pp., November 21, 1888.; 249818 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Daily Post: Fourteenth Year- no. 20: 6pp., April 22, 1898.; 249817 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Daily Post: Sixteenth Year- no. 165: 2pp., September 16, 1900.; 249816 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Houston-Post-Dispatch: features section: 4pp., June 28, 1925.; 249815 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Tri-Weekly Telegraph: 30:174: 4pp., ca. 1865.; 249814 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Tri-Weekly Telegraph: 30:185: 4pp., December 21, 1864.; 249813 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - The Houston Tri-Weekly Telegraph: 31:84: 4pp., September 20, 1865.; 249812 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - New Birmingham Times: 1:7: 4pp., April 6, 1889.; 249811 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - New Birmingham Times: 1:32: 2pp., September 28, 1889.; 249810 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - New Birmingham Times: 1:38: 8pp. (2 parts), November 9, 1889.; 249809 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - New Birmingham Times: 2:8: 8pp. (torn- 2 halves), April 12, 1890.; 249808 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Rusk, TX: The Cherokee Herald: 2:1: 4pp., July 17, 1890.; 249807 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Rusk, TX: The Standard Enterprise: 8:47: 4pp., July 16, 1890.; 249806 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - San Antonio Weekly Herald: 11:2: 2pp., August 26, 1865.; 249805 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Richmond, VA: The Sentinel: 1:135: 2pp., August 19, 1863.; 249804 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)
  - Woodstock, VA: The Tenth Legion: 40:38: 4pp., January 10, 1861.; 249803 (Drawer 37, Folder 3)